Guide to the Friedrich Armand Strubberg Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Friedrich Armand Strubberg collection
1835-1962
WA MSS S-1316
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3
(4 boxes)
The Friedrich Armand Strubberg Collection contains material documenting primarily the early years of the Verein zum Schutz deutscher Einwanderer in Texas, commonly known as the Adelsverein. The Adelsverein was an association of German noblemen, founded in 1842, who hoped to support emigration by German nationals to Texas. The papers consist primarily of correspondence and reports, with some business and legal papers, such as stock certificates, contracts, powers of attorney, receipts, and also some German-language newspapers and a few maps.
Armand, 1806-1889
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Friedrich Armand Strubberg Collection is composed of material which was removed from the Archiv des Vereins zum Schutz deutscher Einwanderer in Texas (WA MSS S-1291). In 1930 the entire Archiv des Vereins was inventoried by the Reichsarchiv in Berlin. When a second inventory was conducted in 1960 by the Staatsarchiv in Marburg, pursuant to sale outside Germany, however, some thirty-eight files were missing. The Strubberg Collection represents approximately forty percent of these missing files. It is assumed that these records were removed in order to provide evidence to exonerate the reputation of Friedrich Armand Strubberg, who was employed by the German Emigration Company as general director of the Nassau Plantation during the late 1840s. He was subsequently removed from this position and sued by the company in 1850 for what would appear to be malfeasance. During this period Strubberg went under the name of Dr. F. A. Shubbert. [It is assumed that this is an Anglicized version of Strubberg. In German-language documents this version is frequently spelled with a "c," i.e. Schubbert.] In many of the files the name Shubbert is underlined in red with further sections underlined and occasionally annotated. Hence these records came to be known as the Strubberg Collection. The trail of the papers from Germany to the United States is unknown. At some time during the 1960s they became the property of Argosy Book Store, Inc. of New York City, where they remained until purchased by The Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library in December 1987. Purchase, 1987.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Friedrich Armand Strubberg Collection, although only three feet in length, holds significant material removed from the Archiv des Vereins zum Schutz deutscher Einwanderer in Texas. The papers consist primarily of correspondence and reports, with some business and legal papers, such as stock certificates, contracts, powers of attorney, receipts, and also some German-language newspapers and a few maps. The material spans the years 1835 to 1962, with the bulk falling between 1846 and 1847. The collection was purchased in 1987 with income from the Frederick W. Beinecke Fund.
The papers are housed in four boxes and divided into four sections. Practically all the files in the Archiv des Vereins are bound. The material which constitutes the Strubberg Collection was separated from the Verein records as whole files and also as single items. The whole files were traceable on the Verein missing folders list and are contained in the first section filed according to the system used in the Archiv des Vereins. Items removed singly are arranged in the remaining three sections. As it was impossible to discern their origin, they have been grouped artificially by subject and record type.
The first section, Verein Files, reflects the founding of the society and contains reports of the directors, commissioners, agents, and other functionaries. These files provide significant information on many leading and influential persons affiliated with the Verein, such as Louis Bené, Henri Alexandre Bourgeois d'Orvanne, P. Cappès, Count Carl of Castell, Prince Carl of Solms-Braunfels, William Henry Daingerfield, Henry Francis Fisher, Count Joseph of Boos-Waldeck, William Kennedy, D. H. Klaener, John O. Meusebach, Burchard Miller, Friedrich von Wrede, and, of course, Friedrich Armand Strubberg, a.k.a. Dr. F. A. Shubbert.
The second section, Miscellaneous Files, represents material which was individually cut out or ripped from bound files in the Archiv des Vereins. As the provenance of this material has been lost, it is now arranged by subject. This section consists of emigrant correspondence, general correspondence, powers of attorney, and a file on damage claims of various emigrants.
The third section, Printed Material, contains items such as pamphlets, receipts, cancelled checks, and contracts, as well as five maps.
The fourth section, Newspapers, contains clippings and also complete issues of German-language newspapers from Germany and Texas from the 1840s and 1850s. Many of those from Germany are special supplements directed to prospective immigrants, listing such things as boat schedules, shipping agents, climatic conditions in America, availability of land, and locations of large German settlements.
German American newspapers; German Americans -- Texas; Comal County (Tex.); Fredericksburg (Tex.); Galveston (Tex.); Germany -- Emigration and immigration; Germany -- History -- 1789-1900; Kassel (Germany); Mainz (Rhineland-Palatinate, Germany); New Braunfels (Tex.); San Antonio (Tex.); Texas -- Emigration and immigration; Texas -- History; Wiesbaden (Germany); Armand, 1806-1889; Bené, Louis; Bourgeois d'Orvanne, Alexander; Cappès, P.; Carl, Count of Castell, 1801-1850; Christian, Count of Neuleiningen-Westerburg; Daingerfield, William Henry, 1808-1878; Dooley, M. A., fl. 1840-1845; Ervendberg, L. C.; Ferdinand, Prince of Solms-Braunfels; Fisher, Henry, fl. 1845; Hermann, Prince of Wied, fl. 1845; Joseph, Count of Boos-Waldeck; Kennedy, William; Klaener, D. H.; Köster, Theodor; Kriedel, W.; Mertz, C. C.; Meusebach, John O., 1812-1897; Miller, Burchard, fl. 1845; Pringle, William; Schütz, C. D. von, Baron; Shubbert, F. A., 1806-1889; Solms-Braunfels, Carl, Prinz zu, 1812-1875; Smith, Ashbel, 1805-1886; Victor, Count of Altleiningen-Westerburg; Wrede, Friedrich W. von; Adelsverein
- Verein Files
  - CA 4 a 1
    - Nr. 2 Gründung des Vereins - Allgemeines -, 1842-48, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - CA 4 b 3
    - Nr. 1 Berichte des Herrn General- kommissär Prinzen Solms Durchl. mit Karten, auch Urkunde über die Grund- steinlegung des Forts Sophienburg mit geschichtlichen Daten über den Verein, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Nr. 5 Korrespondenz mit dem dele- gierten Kommissar in Indian Point, später Galveston, Cappes, 1846-49 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - Nr. 7 Briefe an Cappes 1846 und 1847. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - hierin: Bericht über die Vorgänge in Texas vom Jahre 1846, 1844-47
    - Nr. 8 Korrespondenz mit dem Generalagenten L. Bené, 1846-55, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Nr. 11 Korrespondenz mit Herrn von Meusebach, 1844-51, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
    - Nr. 14 Korrespondenz mit dem Grant-Inhaber und Kolonial-direktor H. Bourgeois d'Orvanne, 1843-53 (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
    - Nr. 18 Administration der Plan- tage Nassau, 1845-53 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Nr. 20 Berichte des Herrn Grafen Boos-Waldeck, insbesondere über die Kolonie Nassau, 1841-44, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - CA 4 b 5
    - Nr. 3 Waisenpflege. - Sanitätsbe- richte, Namen von Waisenkindern, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Nr. 5 Bestallung and Instruktion des General-Kommissärs, Herrn von Meusebach, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 19a)
    - Nr. 8 Druckschriften, Rund- schreiben an die Aktionäre und Akten des Komitees [Stock certificates and contracts], 1842-52 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Nr. 8 Druckschriften, Rund- schreiben an die Aktionäre und Akten des Komitees [Reports], 1849-53 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
    - Nr. 11 Anstellung des Herrn von Schütz in Texas, 1846-47 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - CA 4 c 1
    - Nr. 37 Dienstvertrag mit dem Kolonialarzt Dr. Köster, 1844 Jun 13 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - CA 4 c 2
    - Nr. 2 Papiere des Generalkommis- särs, Prinzen von Solms, Durch- laucht in Texas, 1839-48, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
    - Nr. 4 Allgemeine Gesetze der dritten Sitzung der Legislatur des Staates Texas (ins Deutsche über- setzt von Albert Max von Germar), 1850 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Miscellaneous Files, 1844-53
  - Emigrant correspondence, 1844-53 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Entschädigungsansprüche verschiedener Einwanderer in Texas betr., 1847-49 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - General correspondence [Green Leitz binder] (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - General correspondence, 1846-50 (Box 2, Folder 31-37)
  - General correspondence, 1865-66 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - General correspondence, 1958, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Powers of attorney, 1848-56 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Printed Material, 1835, 1847
  - Pamphlets providing advice to prospective German emigrants (4), 1835, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Receipts and cancelled checks, 1844-54 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Receipts and contracts, 1845, 1854 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Maps (5), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Newspapers, 1845-47, n.d.
  - Clippings, 1845-47, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Issues, 1845-53 (Box 3, Folder 46-51)
  - Issues, 1853 (Box 4, Folder 52)